<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of impeachment exhibited against Col. Robert Gibbons and Cap. Richard Yeardley, late governors of the Isle of Jersey; wherein the several impeachments, notorious actions, high misdemeanours, abominations and oppressions, are laid open, detected, and made publick to the admiring world; as also, a remedy for the people, against the heavy yoke of such tyrannical oppressours, in this juncture of miraculous restauration, after so long a bondage, wherein the little finger of some appeared heavier then the whole loins of others.</title>
            <author>Gibbons, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E989_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E989[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of impeachment exhibited against Col. Robert Gibbons and Cap. Richard Yeardley, late governors of the Isle of Jersey; wherein the several impeachments, notorious actions, high misdemeanours, abominations and oppressions, are laid open, detected, and made publick to the admiring world; as also, a remedy for the people, against the heavy yoke of such tyrannical oppressours, in this juncture of miraculous restauration, after so long a bondage, wherein the little finger of some appeared heavier then the whole loins of others.</title>
                  <author>Gibbons, Robert.</author>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
                  <author>Yeardley, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Horton, living near Cripplegate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's introductory letter dated and signed: Jersey 24. of June 1659, A.B.</note>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 13.".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Huntington Library (Early English books 163:6) and the British Library (Thomason Tracts E.989[20]).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112067:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Articles of Impeachment Exhibited againſt <hi>Col.</hi> ROBERT GIBBONS <hi>AND</hi> Cap. <hi>RICHARD YEARDLEY,</hi> Late Governors of the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN The ſeveral Impeachments, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions, high Miſdemeanours, Abominations and Oppreſſions, are laid open, detected, and made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to the <hi>Admiring World;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO, A <hi>Remedy</hi> for the People, againſt the <hi>Heavy Yoke</hi> of ſuch <hi>Tyrannical Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsours,</hi> in this <hi>Juncture</hi> of <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Reſtauration,</hi> after ſo long a <hi>Bondage,</hi> wherein the <hi>Little Finger</hi> of ſome appeared heavier then the <hi>whole Loins</hi> of others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Horton,</hi> living near Cripplegate, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:112067:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112067:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have taken the opportunity, by a Boat now going for <hi>England,</hi> with Mr <hi>Pemell,</hi> the Chirurgion of this Garriſon, who is ſent with an Addreſs of the Souldiery here, to the Lord <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> and Council of the Army, to let you know, that without diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, you cannot imagine how much the dejected, almost dying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the well-affected people of this Iſle have been revived, and the joy they have had by that unexpected, and almost miraculous reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the famous long-Parliament, to the exerciſe (once again) of their ſupreme trusts, from which they had been ſo long interrupted. And that which hath added to their joy and content, is the Advice we have received from <hi>London,</hi> which doth intimate to us, that there is very great probability, that the people of this poor Iſland (after their long bondage and miſery,) will be delivered from the heavy yoak of their preſent oppreſſors, to wit, from Col. <hi>Robert Gibbons,</hi> and Captain <hi>Richard Yeardley</hi> his Deputy, who, we are credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, appeared in <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere, notorious enemies to that happy reſtauration. It is here affirmed, that Lieut. Col. <hi>Maſon,</hi> is in nomination to be our Governour: we hear a very good report of him, and that he is a profeſſed enemy to Tyranny. In caſe he doth take care to have Officers under him, that may be thus qualified, it will be an honour to him, and great ſatisfaction to all the faithful of this place, who have very much ſuffered under the others; and would have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallably ſuffered in a higher degree, in caſe this ſudden alteration of things had not happened: the Bayliff and others being very much threatned, and that onely for having ſigned a Procuration here to ſome of their faithful Patriots in <hi>London,</hi> which tended onely for the good and ſafety of the whole Iſland. <hi>Benjamin Dumareſy,</hi> the late Protector's Atturney General in this Iſle, was very active againſt the ſaid Bayliff, and others well affected, in oppoſing the ſame in the
<pb facs="tcp:112067:3"/>behalf (as he pretended) of his Maſter the Protector, and the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> and <hi>Yeardley,</hi> to whoſe ſervice he was very zealous againſt the publick good.</p>
            <p>Having ſeen by divers good things publiſht in print, that there are yet (after ſo long Apoſtacy) ſome hopes of just liberty, it hath encouraged me to ſend you here incloſed, thoſe Articles of high miſdemeanours againſt the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> and <hi>Yeardley,</hi> who (in the life of the old Protector, ſo called) were ſent to the Preſident of his Council; but nothing being done therein, 'tis judged fit, not onely by my ſelf, but by ſeveral other honest people of this Iſle, that they might be made publick; for the performance of which, I leave it to your Judgement and Diſcretion, remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Honoured Sir, Your affectionate Friend and Servant, <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Jerſey <date>24. of June 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112067:3"/>
               <head>Articles of miſdemeanours, exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited againſt Col. <hi>Rob: Gibbons,</hi> Governour of the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THat contrary to the ancient Charters and Priviledges of that Iſle and Ordinances made and practiſed thereupon, directing the manner how the quantities of Wooll, Leather, and other Commodities granted to the Iſland and Caſtles, ought to be diſtributed, to wit, by the ſaid Governour, Deputy, Bayliff and Jurats, who thereby are ſtrictly injoyned to ſee that all Bills or Licenſes granted, and Returns thereupon may be regiſtred in the Court of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> by the Clark, paying for each onely 10 pence; but contrary thereunto, the ſaid Col. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> (without the privity of the Bayliff and Jurats, or keeping any Regiſtring thereof) hath granted Licences for the ſaid Commodities, to whom he pleaſed, reſerving for himſelf, Allies, and particular friends, not at all rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Iſland or Caſtles, the greateſt quantity: all which ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and unjuſt proceedings, are very much to the prejudice of the State, and to the Marchants and others of that Iſland: to the State, becauſe none could controle nor check him, either in the granting and diſpoſing of the quantities of the ſaid Commodities, although 20 times more then is allotted to the Iſle and Caſtles, nor in the Returns which he hath made; ſo that any part or parcel of Wool or Leather, hath been tranſported or connived at by him, to be tranſported into <hi>France</hi> for his advantage; being impoſſible to queſtion the Tranſporters. To the Inhabitants, becauſe many of them are denied the benefit of any part of the ſaid Licences: And moſt of thoſe that have any, it is but by very ſmall parcels, as 6, 7, 8, 10, 12, 15, 20, 25, 30, Todds of Wooll, and other Commodities
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112067:4"/>proportionably; for which he hath ſuffered his Clarks to extort from the people one Crown for each Licence, and for the leaſt, half a Crown, which amounts to a conſiderable ſum of money, amongſt the poor Inhabitants.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the ſaid Governour, in order to ſatisfie his unſatiable ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, did contrive another unjuſt way by fleecing the poor Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, in extorting from thoſe that trade out of the Iſland ſix <hi>d.</hi> per head for a Paſſe: which Paſſe, was to continue but for five dayes; and then, if (by contrary winds) they were ſtayed, the ſaid Inhabitants were forced to come to the Caſtles, and there take an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Paſſe, and pay as they did for the former; and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, if the wind had not ſerved in a moneth or more, having extorted the like from all Boats that went but a fiſhing, or fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Sea, weed (called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rack</hi>) with which the Inhabitants do ſoyl their Lands: which exaction is contrary to the Charters and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of that Iſland.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That beſides thoſe forementioned extortions, he the ſaid Governour found out a new one, and that very unjuſt, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable; (<hi>viz.</hi>) by appointing ſome of his Servants and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to drive away the ſheep of the poor Inhabitants to <hi>Mount-Orguil</hi> Caſtle, there committing the poor innocent Creatures pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, upon pretences of having treſpaſſed by entring the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of the State. And that in the Winter ſeaſon, and when there is no graſſe, and that all the Cattle is, by the ancient Lawes and Cuſtoms of that Iſle, known not to be kept in at that time, all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then Common, except incloſures, which are kept by ſtrong ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: the ſaid Servants and Souldiers keeping thoſe poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (contrary to Law, Cuſtoms and Equity) priſoners in the ſaid Caſtle, till the owners did releaſe them, by paying a Ranſom for each head, except for thoſe that were fat, which the Inhabitants could never find nor redeem again, onely the Skins of ſome, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been found, thrown over the walls of the Caſtle of <hi>Mount-Orguil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That it is ſo apparant, that the ſaid Governour hath no other reſpects or care, but to advance his particular gain and profit, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame very openly, upon a Market day in the Iſland, when he had the fleſh of two, or three, or more, fat Oxen to be ſold that day in the Shambles: the Butchers came to him, hearing of a great quantity of Fiſh taken the night before, which was coming
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112067:4"/>to the Market, telling him, that in caſe he ſhould ſuffer the ſaid Fiſh to be brought and ſold that day, he would loſe a great deal upon the ſale of his Beefs: whereupon, the ſaid Governour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding which way the Cart which brought the ſaid Fiſh, did come, commanded ſome of his Souldiers to ſtop it from coming to Market, upon a ſeeming pretence, that one third part thereof belonged unto him; but as ſoon as the Market was over, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed the ſaid Fiſh, which was a very great loſſe to the owners thereof.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That, contrary to Law, and by combination, the ſaid Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hath taken money of perſons in that Iſle, to releaſe Leather, which he had cauſed to be ſeized from them; upon pretence, it was to be tranſported for <hi>France:</hi> and without any legal procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, either in declaring it to the Exchequer, or in the Court of that Iſle, according to the ancient Cuſtom, hath of his own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, freed the ſaid Leather, which afterwards was tranſported into <hi>France.</hi> And namely, from one <hi>John Anquetill</hi> he received 20 Crowns, or thereabouts. And to releaſe Shones and Boots, which his Souldiers had ſeized from one <hi>John Liſcam,</hi> twelve Crowns, and afterwards the ſaid Boots and Shoos were tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. That about <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1655. the ſaid Governour combined with the owners of a great quantity of Tanned-Leather, which came in a Barque from <hi>Waymouth</hi> into the Road of the Iſles, to defraud the State (by pretending the ſaid Leather came from <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and was to be tranſported to St. <hi>Maloes;</hi>) but one <hi>Scouel</hi> Searcher in that Iſle hearing of it, went aboard the ſaid Barque, &amp; finding the ſaid Leather to be Engliſh, made ſeizure of the ſame, and preſently acquainted the ſaid Governour therewith, who did check the ſaid Officer for making ſeizure of Leather, which (as he ſaid) came out of <hi>Ireland:</hi> whereupon, the ſaid <hi>Scouel</hi> went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain aboard the ſaid Barque, carrying with him skilful perſons, who knew the difference between <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> tanned Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who, after a ſtrict ſearch and viſit, found the ſaid Leather to be <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and although the ſaid <hi>Scouel</hi> returned back to the ſaid Governour, acquainting him what further aſſurance he had, that it was <hi>Engliſh</hi> Leather; yet the ſaid Governour perſiſted to be more offended at the ſaid Officer's diligence, and threatned to lay him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112067:5"/>by the heels; and thereupon the ſaid <hi>Scouel</hi> deſiſted, and the ſaid Barque with the ſaid Leather, went for St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> without any further examination, ſoon after the ſaid <hi>Scouel</hi> was by the ſaid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, put out of his place of Searcher: at which proceedings, the ſaid <hi>Scouel</hi> was much diſcontented, and gave out, that he would come into <hi>England,</hi> to complain of the unjuſt actions of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour; but he fearing, leſt the ſaid <hi>Scouel</hi> ſhould complain, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>implace him again in his place of Searcher.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That the ſaid Col. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> notwithſtanding his ſaid extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and that he is allowed pay of Governour, of Captain of Horſe, and Captain of Foot in that Iſland, and pay of Colonel, and of Captain of Horſe and Foot in <hi>England;</hi> beſides ſeveral gifts and grants of his late Highneſs, of other beneficial things in <hi>Kent,</hi> unto him made and granted; and that he receives his ſaid ſeveral Salaries out of the Treaſury in <hi>England:</hi> yet ſo great is his inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable avarice &amp; covetouſneſs, that he is not ſatisfied with the ſame, but hath received out of the publick Revenue of that Iſland in money, Wheat, Rents and profits of divers medows and Paſtures, ſince the time he firſt came thither, to the value of about 2000 <hi>l. ſterling;</hi> for moſt part of which ſum, he hath not accounted at all; and if he hath accounted for any part thereof, he hath had it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain allowed unto him out of the Exchequer, upon ſome preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded disburſements, for Reparations made to <hi>Elizabeth</hi>-Caſtle in that Iſland.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the ſaid Governour, forces the ſaid Inhabitants of that Iſle, (at his will and pleaſure) to come and work at the Caſtle, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> which Caſtle is ſurrounded of the Sea, and the coming in and going out of the ſaid Caſtle, very dangerous, unleſs the Tides are well obſerved, and that for no Salary; and about needleſs Reparations and Fortifications, which have alwayes been pretended neceſſary by the form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Governours, as has been by him: but, indeed and in truth, it is onely to have opportunity, to finger the States-money, which hath alwayes been obſerved, to be pocketted up by them ſo that the State is put to great waſte, and needleſs charges, and the poor people to a great deal of trouble and hazard, by forcing them to work in the Caſtle, (as if they were abſolure ſlaves) and that beyond the time uſed by the worſt of the former Governours, which was onely during one Tide; ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112067:5"/>cruell beyond them, hath the ſaid Governour been againſt the poor people; and particularly againſt thoſe of St. <hi>Laurence</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, whom he cauſed to be kept in at work, during the ſpace of two Tydes, it happening thereupon, that when they were going out of the ſaid Caſtle, in a very obſcure night, five of them were drowned with ſome of their Cattel: the death, or rather the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe perſons, having not ſo much as been examined, or enquired after, although it be evident, their death was occaſioned by the ſaid Governour; and ſome of the Cattel of thoſe poor people, having eſcaped drowning, were found next morning by the Caſtle Walls, and ſeized by his Souldiers as wrack.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That the ſaid Governour, contrary to the Lawes and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of that Iſland, and the Rules of Warres, and by his Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary will hath baſtonaded and miſſ-uſed, (to the indangering of their lives) ſeveral of the Inhabitants, committing them cloſe priſoners, keeping them at his will and pleaſure; and when ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good, releaſes them again, and that without the conſent or knowledge, either of the Juriſdiction of that Iſle, or Council of Warre. And amongſt others, one Mr. <hi>Clement Gallys,</hi> high Conſtable of St. <hi>Saviour,</hi> of above 60 years of Age, and one <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham Beeket</hi> Merchant: both which perſons have very much ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for their affection and faithfulneſs to the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> by the loſſes of their Eſtates, long exile, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and ſeveral others.</p>
               <p n="10">10 That upon an Order coming to the ſaid Iſle, to procure Seamen; and the Inhabitants knowing, that anciently, upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſiderations had by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> of the ſcituation of that Iſle, with the neceſſity of raiſing and maintaining Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Bulwarks round about it, and the conſtant Guards by day and night, that the people are obliged at the ſaid Iſle, being ſo obnoxious to a potent Neighbour, did upon theſe and other weighty Conſiderations, by ſeveral Charters confirmed in the third year of the late Kings Reign, and ſince; by the Council of State-free, and excuſe the Inhabitants of that Iſle from preſſing. And ſome Souldiers coming to the Pariſh of St. <hi>Johns,</hi> to preſſe, one of the Inhabitants, by name <hi>Francis Marret,</hi> who in a civil manner, asked the ſaid Souldier, By what Order they would preſſe the ſaid Inhabitants: whereupon one of the Souldiers anſwered him, he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112067:6"/>wold preſently ſhew him his Warant, which was by Piſtolling him through the head; (ſaying, This was his Commiſſion, or words to the ſame effect) whereof he preſently died. And then fell with his Comerades upon the reſt of the Company, cutting and ſlaſhing them. Notwithſtanding ſuch inhumane murther, proceedings, and cruelties, the ſaid Governour made no more inquiry or examination of the fact, than if the ſaid Souldiers had killed and ſlaſhed ſo many Toads, which indeed was their boaſting after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That divers Souldiers and Seamen pretending to have Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Impreſſe perſons, went about the Iſland and ſeized upon ſeverall young People of good Families, making them believe they ſhould be ſent to <hi>Jamaica;</hi> but in caſe they would give them ſo much money as they demanded (or rather ranſomed them at) they would releaſe them: which their Parents and themſelves not daring to ask them, by what Order they did ſuch things, leſt they ſhould be dealt withall, as the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> and others had been: Therefore did chooſe rather to part with their money to redeem their Children, then to Complain. Which Barbarous and unchriſtian actions, the ſaid Governour connived act, without inflicting any puniſhment upon the Offenders, although they knew as well the ſaid evil practiſes as the former.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That about the month of <hi>January</hi> 1655, the Barque Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure of <hi>Ierſey, John Ahier</hi> Maſter, was taken by an <hi>Oſtendor</hi> near the ſaid Iſle. The ſaid <hi>Ahier</hi> rather then ſuffer the loſſe of all, and to be carryed with many Paſſengers then aboard Captives, did agree with the ſaid <hi>Oſtendor</hi> for the Redemption of his Veſſel and Goods; whereupon he was ſet on Shoare in the ſaid Iſle, to procure the money agreed upon, and to return with ſpeed, which he did, and carryed it aboard, and thereupon his ſaid Veſſel, Paſſengers, and ſo much of the Goods as were left, were freed and brought into the Iſland; where no ſooner he was arrived, but the ſaid Governour ſent for him, calling the ſaid <hi>Ahier</hi> Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, becauſe he had carryed money to the enemy, without firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him therewith, which he could not do by reaſon it was night when he was put a Shoare, and the Tyde up, that none could get into the Caſtle where the ſaid Governour was; and being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to return with ſpeed, the ſaid <hi>Ahier</hi> having by his diligence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112067:6"/>redeemed four times more then he carried, notwithſtanding the ſaid Governour to revenge himſelf of the ſaid <hi>Ahier,</hi> hath refuſed to give him Certificats as he doth to others, of the Landing of ſuch Goods as were not Rifled by the enemy, into the Iſland; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſaid <hi>Ahier</hi> hath ſhewed him Certificats of the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff and Jurats of the Iſle, and of the Searcher there concerning the truth thereof: which injuſtice tends only to endeavour the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the ſaid <hi>Ahier:</hi> who upon the lading at <hi>Hampton</hi> a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Wooll and Leather, hath given ſecurity and bonds of great Sums of money for the Delivery of the ſame in <hi>Jerſey,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Ahier</hi> being in danger that the ſaid Bonds, for want of ſuch Certificats, will be put in proſecution againſt him at the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Court.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That the ſaid Colonel <hi>Gibbons</hi> being appointed by the late Protector and Council one of the Commiſſioners for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding with the Inhabitants of that Iſland, and likewiſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver-General, did contrary to his Inſtructions, and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane-like, as ſoon as the poor Inhabitants had ſubmitted to Compound for their ſmall eſtates, which (of moſt of them) did not conſiſt of above 8, 9.10.12.15.20, pound <hi>per annum,</hi> He the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> would ſend to them to bring and pay their fine, which many could not performe at the very inſtant, whereupon the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> would not give them further time, but would preſently ſend ſuch a number of Troopers to their houſes, and there to abide upon free quarter till the poor people had paid in their money, that in ſeveral houſes the ſaid Troopers did eat and ſpoyle more then the fines of the parties amounted unto. And when the ſufferers went to complain to the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> of their heavy burthens, he would tell them that his ſon and another Souldier would lend them money to pay their ſaid fines, and ſo remove the ſaid Troopers, provided they would enter in bond to repay the ſame within ſuch time as they ſhould limit, and pay him Uſe for the ſame, which proffer many of them were forced (rather than to be utterly ruined) to accept, although the ſame were with ſuch horrid extortion as never was heard to have been practiſed amongſt the worſt of Barbarians, to wit, 20.25. &amp; 30. <hi>per centum,</hi> for each month, and yet the ſaid mony ſo lent, was none of his but of the publique, which he then had in Caſh, or thoſe appointed by him.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112067:7"/>
               <p n="14">14. That the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> knowing ſuch Tyrannical proceedings, were directly contrary to all Law, Juſtice, or Equity, and apprehending that the ſame would be repreſented in <hi>England,</hi> did forbid that any perſon ſhould depart the Iſle without his Paſſe, or any to ſend or carry Letters without firſt bringing them to him to peruſe. And beſides, the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> cauſed all Veſſels to be ſearched for Letters which were bound for <hi>England,</hi> upon which ſearch one Letter of Mr. <hi>Philip Maret</hi> was intercepted as it was ſending into <hi>England,</hi> directed to a Captain that hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been in the Parliament Army, and a great aſſertor of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> which Letter was occaſioned by reaſon of the notorious Tyrannies of the ſaid <hi>Gibbons,</hi> therein fully detected, but particularly of his unjuſt dealings againſt ſeveral well-affected perſons of that Iſland, who although innocent he did not exempt from compounding no more then the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> who had very deeply ſuffered under the enemy, by being declared Traytor by them, and who ſeized and ſequeſtred his Eſtate, by reaſon the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> was in the Parliament quarters, at, and after the late King was put to death; for the Redemption of his Eſtate he was forced to pay to the Enemy a conſiderable ſum of money. Upon which interception the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> committed the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> cloſe Priſoner in <hi>Mout-orguill:</hi> Caſtle, where he kept him 16 months together (moſt part of the time) without Pen, Ink, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or communication with his Friends, being there uſed very B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbarouſly: After which time the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> releaſed him upon Bayl, and then the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> came for <hi>England,</hi> to complain and endeavour to have redreſſe: which the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> diſcovering, told the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> if he would referre the whole buſineſſe to him, he would free him from his troubles, which the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> accepted, by reaſon he obſerved the ſaid <hi>Gibbons</hi> to be very potent at Court, but in lieu of doing according as he had engaged, he the ſaid <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons</hi> attempted by ſureptitious ways to have the Eſtate of the ſaid <hi>Maret</hi> to be forfeited, who for two years together hath waited in <hi>London</hi> upon the ſaid <hi>Gibbons,</hi> being thereby very much damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as well in his bodily health as eſtate, which Impriſonment and troubles hath almoſt brought his antient and weakly Mother to the grave.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112067:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Articles</hi> of miſdemeanours, exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt Cap. <hi>Rich. Yeardley,</hi> Deputy Governour of the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="15">15. THat the ſaid Captain <hi>Richard Yeardley</hi> as Deputy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, hath for theſe late years, contrary to the priviledges granted to the people of that Iſle, taken upon himſelf to diſpoſe of the Licenſes of Wooll, Leather, and other Commodities granted and allotted to the ſaid Iſle, to whom he ſeemeth good; and for his particular gain and advantage, doth ingroſſe a great part of the ſaid Commodities to himſelf, by granting Licenſes to his Servants, Allies, Factors and others, not in the leaſt related to the ſaid Iſle, to the great prejudice and dammage of Merchants and others Inhabitants of that Iſle, amongſt whom, and of right, the ſaid Licenſes ought to be diſtributed; by which unjuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, ſeveral of the ſaid Merchants and Inhabitants, are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to buy the ſaid Licenſes from the ſaid ſtrangers, at very high rates; it being evident, and of certain truth, that a great quanting of the ſaid Commodities, are for his Accounts, and of his Factors and Agents, tranſported into <hi>France,</hi> which cannot be hindered, by reaſon that none can, or dare controle him, either in the diſpoſing the ſaid Licenſes, or in making and giving Returns for the ſeveral Commodities as he doth, and ſeemeth beſt for his advantage, all being at his arbitrary will and diſpoſal; But di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary and againſt the ancient way practiſed in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the ſaid Licenſes; which are to be diſtributed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Bayliff and Juſtices there, and regiſtred in the Court by the Clark, and that for ten pence <hi>per Licence,</hi> whereas the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> ſuffers his Clark to take of the poor Inhabitants five ſhillings, or at leaſt two and ſix pence for every Licence, although but for five todds of wooll.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> contrary to the Law and antient pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the ſaid Iſle, and contrary to the Law of War, hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112067:8"/>by his arbitrary will and pleaſure Impriſoned, and afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed divers of the Inhabitants, namely, one Mr. <hi>Ph. Richar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and laſtly, the High Conſtable, and other Officers of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Brefade,</hi> onely for executing the Duty of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in ſearching a ſuſpected Houſe of the Parriſh (where lived one of his Souldiers) for divers Sheep, and other things that had been ſtollen from ſome of the inhabitants: And that onely by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that it was a Souldier's Houſe; as if Souldiers houſes were Sanctuaries, and not to be ſearched.</p>
               <p n="17">17. That the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> very well knowing that by the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> and for the defence thereof, there ought to be kept twenty Troopers furniſhed with Horſes, for which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there is conſtant pay allowed from the Common-wealth; and yet the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> (Commander in Chief there) connives and ſuffers the Common-wealth to be defrauded, (and the Iſland in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered) by not keeping above twelve Troopers that have Horſes ſerviceable. Some of the Troopers which are in pay ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never a Horſe, and others that have are no way ſerviceable; ſuffering Servants and Children of eleven years of age to be muſtered, and Pay allowed to their Maſters for the ſaid Servants and Children.</p>
               <p n="18">18. That the ſaid Captain <hi>Yeardly</hi> to the very much indange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſafety of the Caſtles, and of that Iſle ſo conſiderable to the Common-wealth, doth ſuffer Souldiers to be lifted in foot Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies that were in actual war in that Iſle againſt the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. That the ſaid Captain <hi>Richard Yeardly,</hi> Deputy Governor of the ſaid Iſle, contrary to the Laws of War, and to the great Scandal of the Government of the Army, and godly people in that Iſle, and ill example to others, doth keep conſtant Company with the moſt notorious Cavalliers of that Iſle, going often to their houſes there to play at Cards, to feaſt and drink healths in ſuch exceſſive manner, that ſeveral times the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> hath ben obſerved to be ſo much diſtempered with Liquor, and ſo drunk, that he could not ſcarce go or ſtand.</p>
               <p n="20">20. That the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> hath ſeveral times vowed, if he ſhould remain in the ſaid Iſle, he would take ſuch courſe that all the Anabaptiſts there ſhould be baniſhed the Iſle.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112067:8"/>
               <p n="21">21. That it is here credibly informed that the ſaid Captain <hi>Richard Yeardly</hi> before and ſince the diſſolving of the late Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, did appear very much diſatisfied of the proceedings of thoſe called Commonwealth men, then ſitting in the ſaid Aſſembly, ſaying, that they were all for <hi>Charles Stuart.</hi> And after the ſaid Aſſembly was diſſolved, he did appear very much diſcontented and diſſatisfied of the ſame, muttering againſt the proceedings of the Army, and pleading openly againſt them and their actions; and for the late Protectors Government, with whom he was the night before the ſaid Diſſolution.</p>
               <p n="22">22. That the ſaid Captin <hi>Richard Yeardly</hi> is ſuch a Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancer of Notorious Cavaliers in that Iſle, that when any well-affected perſons have a Suite or Action at Law againſt them in any thing conſiderable, then the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> upon the day of tryal or hearing of the Cauſe was ſure to come to the Court, and ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally countenanced the Cauſe of ſuch Cavaliers againſt the well-affected, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by his high words &amp; threathings, he did awe the Court in ſuch manner that the well-affected perſons could not have Juſtice: And particularly, about the month of <hi>October</hi> laſt, he appeared for one grand Malignant whom he calls Sr. <hi>Ph. Carteret,</hi> againſt two known well-affected perſons, (by name) Mr. <hi>Thomas Roberts,</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Ricard,</hi> who both of them have much ſuffered for their affection, to the renowned long Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> who did then ſue the ſaid <hi>Carteret</hi> in Court, by vertue of a certain Ordinance of Parliament dated the 16th of <hi>September</hi> 1645. The ſaid well-affected perſons being then railed againſt, and accuſed as if they had been guilty of high Treaſon, to plead againſt the ſaid Delinquent; and the ſaid <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> then Lievtenant of the Train Band of St. <hi>Owens</hi> Parriſh, and the ſaid <hi>Ricard</hi> Enſigne, were both diſmiſſed that day from their Commands, by the ſaid <hi>Yeardly;</hi> for no other offence (known to them) but for pleading againſt a Notorious Malignant.</p>
               <p n="23">23. That the ſaid Captain <hi>Yeardly</hi> being Authorized in that Iſle a Commiſſioner to have an inſpection upon ſuch perſons as ſhould be made choyce of by the People to be Juſtices: He the ſaid <hi>Yeardly</hi> would rather admit, and cauſe to be admitted, ſome that had been in Arms againſt the Parl. to the place of Judicature, then to permitt thoſe which had bin choſen, and had bin great ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112067:9"/>the Parliaments Intereſt, to be admitted in the ſaid place of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Theſe high Miſdemeanours committed and connived at by the ſaid Col. <hi>Rob. Gibbons,</hi> Gove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nour as aforeſaid, and the ſaid <hi>Yeardley</hi> his Deputy, with more of that nature, can be ſufficiently proved, in caſe certain perſons of integrity and honeſty, (having neither relation to the ſaid <hi>Gibbons,</hi> nor to the Iſle, and ſuch as the ſaid Governor may not be a terrour to, as he is to the poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent people there) might go thither with power &amp; authority, not onely to examine the truth of the ſaid Miſdemeanours, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all other grievances of the people: and either to authorize them to reform the ſame, and ſee that the Offendors may receive condigne puniſhment for thoſe enormous and foul Crimes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws and Cuſtoms of that Iſle; or at leaſt, to make their Report upon the whole matter formerly, as upon ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, was practiſed in Caſes of the like nature.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
